Adrian Kohler: Well, we're here today
أدريان كوهلير : نحن هنا اليوم
to talk about the evolution of a puppet horse.
لكي نتحدث عن تطور دُمى الفرس
Basil Jones: But actually we're going to start this evolution
بسيل جونز : ولكننا هنا في الحقيقة لنبدأ الحديث عن هذا التطور
with a hyena.
بهذا الضبع
AK: The ancestor of the horse.
أدريان كوهلير : انه من أسلاف الفرس
Okay, we'll do something with it.
حسناً لقد قمنا بشيء هنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Hahahaha.
ها ها ها ها ها ها ها
The hyena is the ancestor of the horse
ان الضبع هو سلف الفرس
because it was part of a production
لانه جزء من انتاج
called "Faustus in Africa,"
فلم " فاوست أفريقيا "
a Handspring Production from 1995,
من شركة هاندسبرنغ عام 1995
where it had to play draughts with Helen of Troy.
حيث كان يتم تجريب مسودات فلم " هلين تروي "
This production was directed
كان الانتاج من اخراج
by South African artist and theater director,
الفنان والمخرج المسرحي الجنوب افريقي
William Kentridge.
ويليم كينتردج
So it needed a very articulate front paw.
وكان بحاجة لمخالب في بعض المشاهد
But, like all puppets, it has other attributes.
وككل الدمى .. كان يتوجب ان يكون هناك صفات آخرى
BJ: One of them is breath,
بسيل جونز : واحدة من هذه الصفات هي التنفس
and it kind of breathes.
وها هو يتنفس
AK: Haa haa haaa.
أدريان كوهلير : ها .. ها .. ها
BJ: Breath is really important for us.
بسيل جونز : ان التنفس مهم جداً بالنسبة لنا
It's the kind of original movement
انه يمثل الطبيعية في الدمية
for any puppet for us onstage.
التي تظهر على اي منصة عرض
It's the thing that distinguishes the puppet --
انه الشيء الذي يميز بين الدمية ..
AK: Oops.
أدريان كوهلير : عذراً
BJ: From an actor.
بسيل جونز : وبين الممثل
Puppets always have to try to be alive.
انها تحاول دوماً ان تدخل الى الحياة
It's their kind of ur-story onstage,
انها قصة حياتها ..
that desperation to live.
انها تقوم بالمستحيل لكي تبدو حية
AK: Yeah, it's basically a dead object, as you can see,
أدريان كوهلير : ان الدمى هي شيء لا حياة فيه . .كما ترون
and it only lives
وهي تحيا فحسب
because you make it.
لاننا نجعلها كذلك
An actor struggles to die onstage,
ان الممثل يبذل قصارى طاقته لكي يموت على المسرح
but a puppet has to struggle to live.
والدمية تقوم بالمثل لكي تحيا
And in a way that's a metaphor for life.
وهذا الامر بصورة ما .يمثل الحياة ذاتها
BJ: So every moment it's on the stage, it's making the struggle.
بسيل جونز : ان كل لحظة على المنصة .. تمثل صراعاً
So we call this
يمكننا ان ندعو هذه
a piece of emotional engineering
جزء من الهندسة العاطفية
that uses up-to-the-minute
انها تفاعلية تبعاً للحظة
17th century technology --
انها تكنولوجيا تعود الى القرن السابع عشر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
to turn nouns
تقوم بتحويل الاسماء
into verbs.
الى افعال
AK: Well actually I prefer to say
أدريان كوهلير : انا افضل ان اقول
that it's an object
ان هذا جماد
constructed out of wood and cloth
مصنوع من الخشب والاقمشة
with movement built into it
التي تتحرك
to persuade you to believe that it has life.
لكي نحاول ان تقنعك انها على قيد الحياة
BJ: Okay so.
بسيل جونز : حسناً
AK: It has ears that move passively
أدريان كوهلير : ان أذنه تتحرك بصورة تلقائية
when the head goes.
عندما يدور الرأس
BJ: And it has these bulkheads
بسيل جونز : لديه رأس أصم
made out of plywood,
مصنوع من رقائق الخشب
covered with fabric --
تم تغطيته بطبقة قماش
curiously similar, in fact,
انه مشابه في الحقيقة
to the plywood canoes
لزورق الخشب المطاطي
that Adrian's father used to make
التي كان والد آدراين يصنعها
when he was a boy in their workshop.
عندما كان طفلاً في ورشته
AK: In Port Elizabeth, the village outside Port Elizabeth in South Africa.
أدريان كوهلير :في ميناء اليزبيث .. تحديداً في قرية خارج ميناء إليزبيث في جنوب افريقيا
BJ: His mother was a puppeteer.
بسيل جونز : كانت والدته مُحركة دُمى
And when we met at art school
عندما تقابلنا في مدرسة الفن
and fell in love
واعجبنا ببعضنا البعض
in 1971,
عام 1971
I hated puppets.
كنت اكره الدُمى
I really thought they were so beneath me.
لقد كنت أظن انها دون المستوى
I wanted to become an avant-garde artist --
كنت أريد ان اصبح فناناً رائداً
and Punch and Judy was certainly not where I wanted to go.
و " إفتح يا سمسم " و " بنش وجودي " لم يكونا في مجال اهتمامي
And, in fact, it took about 10 years
في الحقيقة لقد تطلب الامر 10 سنوات لكي اغير وجهة نظري هذه
to discover
بسيل جونز : وبالنسبة لي لكي اكتشف
the Bambara Bamana puppets of Mali in West Africa,
مجموعة دُمى بامارو بامبانو من مالي في جنوب افريقا
where there's a fabulous tradition of puppetry,
حيث هناك التقليد الاروع للدُمى
to learn a renewed, or a new, respect
والتي يمكن التعلم منها .. واكتساب مفهوم جديد عنها
for this art form.
لهذا الشكل من الفن
AK: So in 1981, I persuaded Basil and some friends of mine
أدريان كوهلير : في عام 1981 حاولت اقناع بسيل واصدقاء لي
to form a puppet company.
لكي نؤسس شركة دُمى
And 20 years later, miraculously,
وبعد 20 عام . .بصورة مفاجئة
we collaborated with a company from Mali,
استطعنا ان نتعاون مع شركة من مالي
the Sogolon Marionette Troupe of Bamako,
هي " سوجولون مارينيت تورب اوف باماكو "
where we made a piece about a tall giraffe.
حيث صنعنا هناك الزرافة الطويلة
It was just called "Tall Horse," which was a life-sized giraffe.
انه ما ندعوه " الحصان الطويل " شيء بحجم الزرافة
BJ: And here again, you see the same structure.
بسيل جونز : وهنا يمكنكم ان تروا ايضاً نفس البنية
The bulkheads have now turned into hoops of cane,
الخشب الاصم بات الآن قصباً
but it's ultimately the same structure.
ان البنية هي ذاتها للامرين
It's got two people inside it on stilts,
هناك شخصين في الداخل
which give them the height,
وهذا ما يعطي المجسم الارتفاع
and somebody in the front
وشخص في المقدمة امام المجسم
who's using a kind of steering wheel to move that head.
والذي يحرك العجلة .. والرأس
AK: The person in the hind legs
أدريان كوهلير : الشخص الذي يقف في المؤخرة
is also controlling the tail, a bit like the hyena --
يتحكم في الذيل .. شيء يشبه الضبع
same mechanism, just a bit bigger.
نفس الميكانيكية .. ولكن اكبر
And he's controlling the ear movement.
وهو يتحكم بحركة الأذن
BJ: So this production
بسيل جونز :هذا التصميم
was seen by Tom Morris
شاهده توم موريس
of the National Theatre in London.
في المسرح القومي في لندن
And just around that time,
وفي تلك الاثناء
his mother had said,
كانت قد قالت له والدته
"Have you seen this book by Michael Morpurgo
هل قرأت الكتاب الذي كتبه ميشيل موربوجو
called 'War Horse'?"
الذي يدعى .. حصان الحرب؟
AK: It's about a boy who falls in love with a horse.
أدريان كوهلير : انه عن طفل وقع في حب فرس
The horse is sold to the First World War,
وتم بيعه لكي يشارك في الحرب العالمية الاولى
and he joins up to find his horse.
ومن ثم انخرط في الجيش لكي يبحث عن الفرس
BJ: So Tom gave us a call and said,
بسيل جونز : فاتصل بنا جونز وقال لنا ..
"Do you think you could make us a horse
هل تظنون انه من الممكن صناعة فرس
for a show to happen at the National Theatre?"
للعرض في المسرح القومي ؟
AK: It seemed a lovely idea.
أدريان كوهلير : لقد بدت فكرة رائعة
BJ: But it had to ride. It had to have a rider.
بسيل جونز : ولكن كان يجب ان يمتطيه فارس ..
AK: It had to have a rider,
أدريان كوهلير : كان يتوجب وجود فارس ..
and it had to participate in cavalry charges.
وكان يتوجب ان يشارك مع رعيل الخيل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
A play about early 20th century plowing technology
انه عرض بتقنيات القرن العشرين
and cavalry charges
مع رعيل خيل من التاريخ
was a little bit of a challenge for the accounting department
لقد كان الامر مكلفاً على قسم المحاسبة
at the National Theatre in London.
المسرح القومي في لندن
But they agreed to go along with it for a while.
ولكنهم وافقوا على المضي قدماً في ذلك
So we began with a test.
لذا شرعنا في اختبار النماذج
BJ: This is Adrian and Thys Stander,
بسيل جونز : هذا آدريان و ثايس ستاندر
who went on to actually design the cane system for the horse,
الذين صمموا الهيكل الاساسي للفرس
and our next-door neighbor Katherine,
وجارتنا كاثرين
riding on a ladder.
تمتطي الفرس
The weight is really difficult when it's up above your head.
كان الوزن محورياً اذ انه سيحمل على الممثلين
AK: And once we put Katherine
أدريان كوهلير : وما ان امتطت كاثرين
through that particular brand of hell,
شعرنا بنشوة هائلة
we knew that we might be able to make a horse, which could be ridden.
لاننا ايقنا انه بالامكان صناعة فرس يمكن امتطاءه
So we made a model.
ومن ثم صنعنا نموذج اولي للعرض
This is a cardboard model,
هذا نموذج خشبي
a little bit smaller than the hyena.
انه اصغر قليلاً من الضبع
You'll notice that the legs are plywood legs
سوف تلاحظون الواح الخشب التي تشكل الارجل
and the canoe structure is still there.
وكيف ان القصب استخدم ايضاً
BJ: And the two manipulators are inside.
بسيل جونز : والمتحكمين .. في الداخل
But we didn't realize at the time
ولكن لم ندرك في هذه الاثناء
that we actually needed a third manipulator,
اننا سنحتاج متحكم ثالث
because we couldn't manipulate the neck
لان التحكم في الرقبة
from inside
لايمكن ان يتم من الداخل
and walk the horse at the same time.
كما الاشراف على عملية سيره
AK: We started work on the prototype
أدريان كوهلير : بدأنا العمل على النموذج
after the model was approved,
بعد ان تمت الموافق على النموذج الاولي
and the prototype took a bit longer
واحتاجت صناعة المجسم وقتاً اطول
than we anticipated.
مما كنا نتوقع
We had to throw out the plywood legs and make new cane ones.
لقد استغنينا عن ارجل الواح الخشب .. واستعضنا عنها بالقصب
And we had a crate built for it.
ومن ثم ربطنا الاحزمة
It had to be shipped to London.
لكي يتم نقله الى لندن
We were going to test-drive it on the street outside of our house in Cape Town,
كنا قد قمنا بتجربة قيادته في شوارع كيب تاون ( عاصمة جنوب افريقيا )
and it got to midnight and we hadn't done that yet.
وكان الليل قد انتصف .. ولم نجرب ذلك من قبل
BJ: So we got a camera,
بسيل جونز : احضرنا كاميرا تصوير
and we posed the puppet
ومن ثم وضعنا المجسم بوضعية مميزة
in various galloping stances.
تعبر عن وضعيات الحركة
And we sent it off
ومن ثم ارسلناه
to the National Theatre,
الى المسرح القومي
hoping that they believed
لكي نأمل ان يقتنع المسؤلون
that we created something that worked.
انه بالامكان صناعة شيء يمكنه الايفاء بالغرض المطلوب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
AK: A month later, we were there in London
أدريان كوهلير : بعد شهر .. كنا في لندن
with this big box and a studio full of people about to work with us.
مع معدات كثيرة .. واستديو مليء بالاشخاص لكي يعملوا معنا
BJ: About 40 people.
بسيل جونز : نحو 40 شخص
AK: We were terrified.
أدريان كوهلير : كنا خائفين
We opened the lid, we took the horse out,
فتحنا الطرد .. اخرجنا الفرس
and it did work; it walked and it was able to be ridden.
ونجح النموذج .. سار .. وتم امتطائه
Here I have an 18-second clip
لدينا ملف فيديو طوله 18 ثانية
of the very first walk of the prototype.
عن اول خطوة للنموذج
This is in the National Theatre studio,
هذا المسرح القومي في لندن
the place where they cook new ideas.
انه المكان الذي تطبخ فيه الافكار الجديدة
It had by no means got the green light yet.
ولكن لم يكن يعني هذا اننا حصلنا على الضوء الاخضر للشروع بالعمل
The choreographer, Toby Sedgwick,
مصمم الرقصات " توبي سيدجويك "
invented a beautiful sequence
كان قد نسق تتابع مميز جداً
where the baby horse,
حيث ينمو مُهر صغير
which was made out of sticks and bits of twigs,
مصنوع من بضع عيدان وقطع من الاغصان
grew up into the big horse.
الى فرس كبير
And Nick Starr, the director of the National Theatre,
ومخرج المسرح القومي نيك ستار
saw that particular moment, he was standing next to me -- he nearly wet himself.
رآى هذا المشهد .. وقد دمعت عيناه - كان واقفاً بقربي -
And so the show was given the green light.
وحينها اُعطي المشروع الضوء الاخضر
And we went back to Cape Town and redesigned the horse completely.
ومن ثم عدنا الى كيب تاون . .واعدنا تصميم الفرس بصورة تامة
Here is the plan.
وهذه هي الخطة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And here is our factory in Cape Town
هنا مصنع في كيب تاون
where we make horses.
حيث كنا نصنع فيه الفرس
You can see quite a lot of skeletons in the background there.
يمكنكم ان تروا الكثير من الهياكل
The horses are completely handmade.
والخيول بأكملها مصنوعة يدوياً
There is very little 20th century technology in them.
وهناك القليل من التكنولوجيا فيها
We used a bit of laser cutting on the plywood
فقد استخدمنا الليزر لتقطيع الاخشاب
and some of the aluminum pieces.
وبعض قطع الألومنيوم
But because they have to be light and flexible,
والتي يجب ان تكون خفيفة ومرنة
and each one of them is different,
وكل واحدة منها مختلفة
they can't be mass-produced, unfortunately.
لا يمكن صناعة كمية كبيرة منها لسوء الحظ
So here are some half-finished horses
هنا ترون خيول نصف منتهية
ready to be worked in London.
جاهزة للانتقال الى لندن لكي يتم العمل عليها
And now we would like to introduce you
وسوف نقدم لكم
to Joey.
الآن .. "جوي"
Joey boy, you there?
جوي هل انت هنا
Joey.
جوي
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Joey, come here.
جوي تعال الى هنا
No, no, I haven't got it.
لا .. لا .. لم اطاله
He's got it; it's in his pocket.
انه في جيبه
BJ: Joey.
بسيل جونز : "جوي"
AK: Joey, Joey, Joey, Joey.
أدريان كوهلير : "جوي""جوي""جوي""جوي"
Come here. Stand here where people can see you.
تعال إلى هنا ..لكي يراك الناس
Move around. Come on.
تحرك .. تعال
I'd just like to describe --
اريد فقط ان اشرح
I won't talk too loud. He might get irritated.
لا اريد ان ارفع من صوتي .. لكي لا اوتره
Here, Craig is working the head.
هنا كريغ يتحكم بالرأس
He has bicycle brake cables
هنا لديه جنزير دراجة هوائية
going down to the head control in his hand.
يهبط من الرأس الى يديه
Each one of them
كل واحد منهما
operates either an ear, separately,
يتحكم باحدى الأُذنين .. بصورة مختلفة
or the head, up and down.
او لرفع الراس
But he also controls the head directly
وهو يتحكم بالراس مباشرة
by using his hand.
باستخدام يديه ايضا
The ears are obviously
الأذنين كما هو واضح
a very important emotional indicator of the horse.
لهما اهمية كبيرة للتدليل على حالة الفرس النفسية
When they point right back,
عندما تشير الى الخلف
the horse is fearful or angry,
يعني ان الفرس خائف او غضب
depending upon what's going on in front of him, around him.
وهذا يعتمد على ما يوجد امامه .. او حوله
Or, when he's more relaxed, the head comes down
وعندما يكون مرتاحاً .. يهبط الرأس الى الاسفل
and the ears listen, either side.
والاذنين ترتاح وتستمع لكل الطرفين
Horses' hearing is very important.
ان سمع الفرس ضروري جداً
It's almost more important than their eyesight.
كما نظره
Over here,
هنا
Tommy's got what you call the heart position.
تومي موجود في موقع القلب
He's working the leg.
انه يتحكم في الارجل
You see the string tendon from the hyena,
ويمكنكم ان تروا كيفية التحكم يشابه الضبع
the hyena's front leg,
انها رجل ضبع امامية
automatically pulls the hoop up.
وهو يمكنه ان يسحب الجسد
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Horses are so unpredictable.
لا يمكن توقع تصرفات الاحصنة
The way a hoof comes up with a horse
ان طريقة ارتفاع الجسد مع الفرس
immediately gives you the feeling
تعطي انطباع مباشر عن مشاعره
that it's a convincing horse action.
وهي مفيدة للاقناع بحيوية الفرس
The hind legs have got the same action.
ان الارجل تتحرك بنفس الطريقة
BJ: And Mikey also has,
بسيل جونز : وميكي يملك ايضاً
in his fingers,
في اصابعه
the ability to move the tail
القدرة على تحريك الذيل
from left to right,
من اليمنة الى اليسرة
and up and down with the other hand.
والى الاعلى الى الاسفل عبر اليد الثانية
And together, there's quite a complex possibility
وبواسطتهما .. يمكن الحصول على درجات حركة كبيرة
of tail expression.
للتعبير عن حالة الذيل
AK: You want to say something about the breathing?
أدريان كوهلير : هل تريد ان تقول شيئاً عن التنفس
BJ: We had a big challenge with breathing.
بسيل جونز : كان لدينا تحد كبير بخصوص التنفس
Adrian thought
فكر أدريان
that he was going to have to split the chest of the puppet in two
ان نفصل صدر الدُمية الى قسمين
and make it breathe like that --
وان نجعله يتنفس هكذا
because that's how a horse would breathe, with an expanded chest.
لانه هذه هي الطريقة التي تتنفس فيها الخيل .. انه يوسع صدره
But we realized
ولكن ادركنا لاحقاً
that, if that were to be happening,
انه .. ان سيتوجب القيام بذلك
you wouldn't, as an audience, see the breath.
لن يستطيع الجمهور ان يرى عملية التنفس
So he made a channel in here,
لذا قام بوضع قناة هنا
and the chest moves up and down in that channel.
والصدر يتحرك الى الاعلى والاسفل في هذه القناة
So it's anti-naturalistic really, the up and down movement,
انها عكس الطبيعة بسبب حركتها الى الاعلى والاسفل
but it feels like breath.
ولكنها تشابه التنفس
And it's very, very simple
انها بسيطة جدا
because all that happens
ان كل ذلك يتم التحكم فيه بواسطة
is that the puppeteer breathes with his knees.
هي تلك الدمية التي تتنفس بـ ركبتيها
AK: Other emotional stuff.
أدريان كوهلير : اما فيما يخص العواطف
If I were to touch the horse here
ان لمست الفرس هنا
on his skin,
على بشرته
the heart puppeteer can shake the body from inside
يمكن للشخص الواقف في وضعية القلب .. ان يهز الجسد من الداخل
and get the skin to quiver.
ويجعل البشرة ترتجف
You'll notice, of course,
سوف تلاحظون ..حتماً
that the puppet is made out of cane lines.
ان الدمية مصنوعة من خطوط من القصب
And I would like you to believe that it was an aesthetic choice,
صحيح اريد ان تظنوا ان هذا الخيار جمالي
that I was making a three-dimensional drawing of a horse
لانني عندما كنت اصنع الرسومات ثلاثية الابعاد للفرس
that somehow moves in space.
والتي يمكنها ان تتحرك في الفراغ
But of course, it was the cane is light,
ادركنا ان القصب هو خيار ملائم لانه خفيف
the cane is flexible, the cane is durable
مرن .. ويمكن الحصول عليه
and the cane is moldable.
وتشكيله
And so it was a very practical reason why it was made of cane.
لذا من العملي جدا صناعة الهيكل من القصب
The skin itself
البشرة ذاتها
is made out of a see-through nylon mesh,
مصنوعة من خليط نيلوني
which, if the lighting designer
والذي يمكن لمهندس الاضاءة
wants the horse to almost disappear,
اخفاء الفرس تماما
she can light the background
باضاءة الخلفية
and the horse becomes ghostlike.
فيصبح كما الشبح
You see the skeletal structure of it.
يمكنكم ان تروا الهيكل العظمي
Or if you light it from above, it becomes more solid.
وان تمت الاضاة من الاعلى .. يمكن ان تبدو صلبة
Again, that was a practical consideration.
ومرة اخرى لاسباب عملية
The guys inside the horse have to be able to see out.
كان يتوجب على الاشخاص في الداخل من الحصول على زوايا رؤية
They have to be able to act
من اجل التفاعل
along with their fellow actors in the production.
مع محيطهم من الممثلين
And it's very much an in-the-moment activity that they're engaged in.
وهذا ضروري في خضم العرض
It's three heads making one character.
في الخلاصة انها شخصية واحدة بثلاث عقول
But now we would like you to put Joey through some paces.
والان نريد ان نأخذ " جوي " في جولة
And plant.
لكي يأكل بعض الاعشاب
(Whinny)
(صهيل)
Thank you.
شكراً
And now just --
والآن فحسب ..
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
All the way from sunny California
الى كاليفورنيا المشمسة ..
we have Zem Joaquin
هنا لدينا .. زيم خواكين
who's going to ride the horse for us.
والتي سوف تمتطي الفرس من اجلنا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Music)
(موسيقى)
So we would like to stress
علينا ان نقول
that the performance you see in the horse
ان الاداء الذي يتم هنا
is three guys
هو لثلاثة اشخاص
who have studied horse behavior incredibly thoroughly.
درسوا تصرفات الاحصنة بصورة معمقة
BJ: Not being able to talk to one another
بسيل جونز : ولا يستطيعون التواصل فيما بينهم
while they're onstage
عندما يكونون على المنصة
because they're mic'd.
لان المنصة مليئة بالميكرفونات
The sound that that very large chest makes, of the horse --
لكي يظهر صوت صدر الفرس الكبير
the whinnying and the nickering and everything --
وصوته .. وحركة حوافره وكل شيء
that starts usually with one performer,
الذي يبدأ عادة بمؤد واحد
carries on with a second person
والذي يحمل الآخر
and ends with a third.
وينتهي بالثالث
AK: Mikey Brett from Leicestershire.
أدريان كوهلير : ميكي بيت من ليسترشيرن
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Mikey Brett, Craig, Leo,
ميكي بريت . كريغ .. ليو
Zem Joaquin and Basil and me.
زيم خواكين .. بسيل .. و أنا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you.
شكراً .. شكراً